<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from Holland: being a true relation of all the proceedings of the Northern armies. Under the command of Duke Hamilton, the Earl of Lendrick, the Lord Calander, Monroe, Sir Marmaduke Langdale, Sir Thomas Tilsley. And the rest of the English in the Northern Parts. Sent from a gentleman in Holland, to his friend here in England: which hath set down all the passages of the armies. Sept.23.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1476</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E467_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205265</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864682</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864682</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E467[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from Holland: being a true relation of all the proceedings of the Northern armies. Under the command of Duke Hamilton, the Earl of Lendrick, the Lord Calander, Monroe, Sir Marmaduke Langdale, Sir Thomas Tilsley. And the rest of the English in the Northern Parts. Sent from a gentleman in Holland, to his friend here in England: which hath set down all the passages of the armies. Sept.23.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1648. Octob.12.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hamilton, James Hamilton, --  Duke of, 1606-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:116914:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A Letter from HOLLAND: BEING A true Relation of all the proceedings of THE Northern Armies.</p>
            <p>UNDER The Command of Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Lendrick,</hi> the Lord <hi>Calander, Monroe,</hi> Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Tilſley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND The reſt of the Engliſh in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Parts.</p>
            <p>Sent from a Gentleman in <hi>Holland,</hi> to his friend here in <hi>England:</hi> Which hath ſet down all the Paſſages of the Armies. <hi>Sept.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>Printed in the year, 1648, <hi>Octob.</hi> 12.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:116914:2"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving continued with the Scottiſh Army, till the disbanding at Vtoxater in Staffordſhire, (it being impoſſible, for thoſe, who were ſo buſie about plunder and booty, not to have ſome of us eſcape) I made ſhift, by the benefit of the Engliſh tongue to come to Boſton, where after ſome ſtay for winde, I embarked and arrived here the of the preſent.</p>
            <p>During our former correſpondence from Edenburgh, I adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed you of my incapacity of imployment in the Scottiſh Army, in regard of my former activeneſſe againſt thoſe of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; yet retaining ſtill ſome hopes of command, either there, or with Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale,</hi> (at leaſt my affection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained it) I marched along, frequenting (the moſt I could) the head quarters, aſwell to ſollicite my own advancement, as for obſervation, which hath enabled me for the enſuing relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being truly ſet down, without favour or any private intereſt or conſideration; for ſatisfaction of all his Majeſties Subjects, and eſpecially your ſelf, who is ſo great a lover of truth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though malice, ignorance, or lying ſpirits may ſuggeſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, yet not to be credited.</p>
            <p>I have likewiſe acquainted you (weekly as it did occurre) with the great oppoſition, made both in the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and otherwiſe againſt the preparation and leavy of the late Army, proceeding not from any Piety or Religion, as thoſe oppoſers pretended, nor from any affection to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or Army of <hi>England,</hi> but from meer ſelf-ends, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to admit of any equallity, or let go any part of the power and ſway, which for many years they had carried in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and fearing they ſhould want the command and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Army, and ſo diſabled for want of intereſt therein to convert the ſame to benefit, and for ſerving their own turns as occaſion offered: the which, being ſtrongly backed with the dayly papers, preaching, and diſwaſion of ſeditious corrupted
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:116914:2"/>
Miniſters (though at laſt fruſtrated by the great dexterity, and diligence of the well affected party) protracted ſo much time before things were brought to a head, as gave no ſmall advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the contrary Armies of <hi>England,</hi> but was a great cauſe of the ill ſucceſſe that hapned afterwards to the late Army, as is obvious to any indifferent judgement.</p>
            <p>About the middle of <hi>June,</hi> there appeared in the Weſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for obſtruction of the leavy, about 3000. men in a hoſtile manner, which did neceſſitate the drawing thither of moſt of the horſe, that was in readineſſe, (which lay at a great diſtance, diſperſed through the kingdom, and had no ſmall toil to come together) with ſome foot for their ſuppreſſion: which under the conduct of the Earl of <hi>Calander,</hi> L. Gen. of the Army, and <hi>Middleton</hi> Lieu. Gen. of the horſe, was atchieved, and at Machlin Moore, thoſe rebels were routed and diſperſed.</p>
            <p>Within few dayes after, the Gen. receives order from the Committee of Eſtates, that all the forces of horſe and foot, that were raiſed, ſhould ſpeedily march to the Engliſh borders, aſwell to prevent ſuch incurſions, which Major Gen <hi>Lambert</hi> (being there with his Army) might make upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> as for ſecuring of <hi>Carlile</hi> (then poſſeſſed by the Engliſh) which was reduced to no ſmall extremity by <hi>Lamberts</hi> forces, the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or loſſe of which in the conſideration of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was of great concernment.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, upon the 4. of <hi>July</hi> about 2500 horſe and 2000. foot rendezvouzed at Annan, which being ſo ſmall a number, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned our ſtay there for four dayes, to expect more forces, and without any great increaſe we marched into <hi>England,</hi> on Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following, <hi>July</hi> the 8. and that night quartered at Roclifle four miles ſhort of Carlile.</p>
            <p>The next day, the Lord Gen. receiving from Sir <hi>Philip Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> the keyes of Carlile Caſtle, we marched to Thuresby, four miles on the other ſide that City, where the Infantry is quartered, and by this time a few Regiments more of foot was come to us, but the whole not conſiderable to run the hazzard of a re-encounter with Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> then about Penreth (ſixteen miles diſtant) with a great force, by report, it was thought fit we ſhould remain ſome time at Thuresby to receive a greater ſtrength, and that the Duke might ſettle the garriſon of Carlile, which few dayes after was accompliſht, as likewiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116914:3"/>
the ſouldier have ſome refreſhment, after a weariſome march, through abundance of rain and waters.</p>
            <p>On Friday the 14. we advanced with the whole, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3000 horſe and 4000 foot towards Penreth, fully reſolved to poſſeſſe that town, or fight with Major Gen. <hi>Lambert;</hi> but by reaſon of the length of the way, moſt of our horſe quarters being above twenty miles from thence, and ſome narrow paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (which much retarded) we were benighted three miles ſhort of Penreth, and therefore quartered in the field that night, not expoſing our ſelves to the diſadvantage of making an onſet at a time ſo unſeaſonable.</p>
            <p>The next morning at five a clock, the Cavalry advanced to Penreth (the foot following after) where we found, that <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> with his Army, had marched away about midnight to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Appleby, (a garriſon of theirs) and having advanced two miles beyond the town, our horſe intending to purſue him, the intelligence of the countreymen, did aſſure his being by that time at Appleby, whereto there was about eight miles, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall waters unpaſſable betwixt us, by means of the great rain that fell in ſuch abundance, the which occaſioned our quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſaturday night, and ſunday, at and about Penreth.</p>
            <p>Munday morning, notwithſtanding of the great deluge of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, it continually raining, we marched for Appleby, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching near unto it with our horſe, we diſcovered a great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Major Gen. <hi>Lamberts</hi> Cavalry, which ſome of ours pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently charged, and put to their retreat into the town of Apple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; Collonel <hi>Harriſon</hi> who commanded the enemies party, was there wounded with divers others, and ſome ſlain, the reſt eſcaping by means of the barricado on the bridge, which was ſtrongly manned with muſqueteers, and could not poſſibly with our horſe be forced, all our foot being far behinde us; here our Cavalry ſtaid in expectation of the foots coming, and to try if it was poſsible to go on the other ſide of the river, where <hi>Lamberts</hi> Army was, (a great part in ſight) it was found alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether infeazible, ſo great was the inundation that no place within ten miles was fordable: In the evening ſome foot came to us, who during the ſmall remnant of the day endeavoured to gain the bridge, which by the night was prevented, ſome of each ſide being ſlain, and wounded, of ours one taken priſoner, of theirs Lieu. <hi>Sheares,</hi> and five others, which next day without
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116914:3"/>
any exchange, were by the Gen. freely diſcharged and ſent to <hi>Lambert.</hi> Our Cavalry, all that night remained in the field near Appleby, and the foot for the moſt part three miles ſhort of it at Kirby Thure, being unable to paſſe there, a river (which at other times very ſmall, but) now ſo ſwoln, as that no horſe could come through it without great perill<hi>:</hi> That night likewiſe <hi>Lambert</hi> (leaving the garriſon ſtill at Appleby) marched away with his Army over Stainemoore, into the confines of Yorkeſhire, and the Biſhoprick, and the next day our horſe were diſpoſed into ſeverall quarters.</p>
            <p>At Kirby Thure we ſtaid a fortnight, which though it may ſeem long, yet was it neceſſary and requiſite, in reſpect we ſtill wanted the main ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials and ſinews of the Army (occaſioned by our ſuddain and unready departure from <hi>Scotland,</hi> and afterwards by the unpaſſableneſſe of the way with the deep waters) there being in ſtore with us no more then ten barrels of pouder, other ammunition proportionable, no artillery at all, no meal, but a little for the ſouldiers ſubſiſtance ſome dayes on the way: they were to march hence, the Countrey being unable and unwilling to furniſh any, and the Iriſh and the moſt conſiderable part of the main Army it ſelf, as yet not come out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> all which was conceived (upon a very deliberate conſultation) had we precipitated, our advance might have become uſeleſſe, if not loſt by the interpoſition of enemies or ſome other incident; Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, ſo ſoon as a few Regiments came to us, (though many ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde of horſe and foot) and that we had got a little more meal, with a fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting proportion of ammunition: we marched forwards, though the Cannon, a great part of the forces, and the Iriſh were ſtill far ſhort of us; by our ſtay here, we reaped another advantage, the reducing of Appleby, of great importance, ſtanding on a paſſe very uſefull and neceſſary, for going to, and from the Army.</p>
            <p>Before removall from Kirby Thure, in a full councell of war, after much debate and many arguments, pro and con, it was carried that the Army ſhould march to Lancaſhire, and not Yorkſhire, which afterwards was ſuppoſed to be diſadvantagious.</p>
            <p>From thence, in two dayes we marched to Kendale, where it was thought fit, before going too far, to abide few dayes for Major Gen. <hi>Monro,</hi> his nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer coming to us; as alſo ſome more of the Scottiſh forces, and before his conjunction with the Army (few Regiments more being come up) or that we well knew how far from us was the Cannon: we went from thence to Hornby within Lancaſhire, where after a little abode, more of our forces (though not the whole) did overtake us. On the 13. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> moſt part of the Cavalry, by the reſolve of moſt of the chief officers at a conſultation, advanced beyond Preſton in that County, an inevitable neceſſity ſo to do, being concluded for enlarging of quarters, the Countrey about Hornby diſtitute of proviſion for horſe and man (the Army by this time being grown more numerous) and for avoiding of the inconveniences, we muſt infallibly have been expoſed unto, had the horſe and foot, marched at one time through ſuch continued ſtraight lanes, as that Countrey doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with, which were then exceeding deep and myrie, it was no ſmall difficulty to perſwade the Duke to conſent to this reſolution; for incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently after the councell was diſſolved, a great officer of horſe, ſpeaking concerning it, and joyfull with the hopes of better quarter, ſaid that the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116914:4"/>
Generall was very unwilling, that the horſe ſhould ſo far ſeparate; but told me further, he knew not what prejudice it could any way produce, and that if it had not been granted, a generall diſcontent would unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have followed amongſt the Cavalry: At Hornby the Gen. ſtaies after the horſe had marched, for conducting of the foot, and taking care to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide carriage for, and ſending along the ammunition, as his manner was in all other places, which <hi>I</hi> thought was ſuch a drudgery to a Generall, conſidering the unwillingneſſe of the Countrey every where, to ſend in horſes, as few men in ſuch command would have undergone.</p>
            <p>Upon the 14. <hi>Monroe</hi> with his forces came to Kirby Lanſdale, within ten miles of us, where he received the Generals order to ſtay there, till the Cannon and the reſt of the Ammunition came to him, and then to bring all to the Army: On which day the Duke marched away with the Infantrie, and Ammunition, and without ſtaying any more then one night in a place, came to the Moore near Preſton on the 17. in the morning, where the foot was drawn up, no knowledge of any enemy to be near us as yet, onely ſome intelligence came the night before, that part of their forces were quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered within leſſe then twelve miles, the which, in leſſe then an hour after was contradicted by an eminent perſon, and ſo the former diſcredited: that night two of our Collonels of horſe had their quarters beaten up, one man killed, and divers conſtrained to ſave themſelves by ſwimming of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, yet were they all ſo negligent, as to give the Gen. no advertiſement of it: After a ſmall ſtay on the Moore, the foot had order to march to their quarters appointed for that night, being on the other ſide of Preſton bridge, where the Duke himſelf as he was accuſtomed, went before hand, with ſome other officers to view the place, who preſently returning towards the Moore, receives notice, that ſome ſmall parties of the enemies horſe were diſcovered on the other ſide of the Moore, which his Grace finding to be true, and that they were skirmiſhing in a narrow lane, with the rear of Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdales</hi> foot, though not ſuſpecting that the whole ſtrength of the enemy was ſo near hand; he preſently diſpatched order, that Lieu. Gen. <hi>Middleton,</hi> who was about ten miles beyond us, ſhould with all expedition march there to us, with the Cavalry, and gave command to <hi>Baylie</hi> Lieu. Gen. of the foot, to draw them all in order on the Moore, and not to paſſe the bridge, intending to fight with the enemy, if need required it; there being as yet no horſe come to us, ſave the Generals own troop; ſuch Regiments of horſe as were not ſent with <hi>Middleton,</hi> being ſtill in their quarters, not knowing anything of this occaſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lieu. Gen. <hi>Baylie</hi> cauſes the foot to ſtay accordingly: which the Earl of <hi>Calander</hi> perceiving, he ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly adviſeth, that it was ſafeſt the foot ſhould forthwith march to their quarters, where they might the ſooner receive ſuccour from the Cavalry, which was on the ſame ſide of the river; that the enemy (probably) had but an inconſiderable force there, wherewith Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdales</hi> forces would be able to deal with the help of part of our horſe, that was begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to advance towards us, (not thoſe with <hi>Middleton)</hi> that if in caſe the enemy had there his whole force, he might eaſily with his horſe come about, and overrun the foot, if they ſtaid on the Moore, they wanting our Cavalry to aſſiſt them; but if they paſſed the water, not onely they would be in ſafety, but alſo Sir <hi>Marmaduke</hi> (whether the enemy had his whole ſtrength
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116914:4"/>
there or not) would by degrees, be able to draw off his men to our foot, on the other ſide, and then both forces might joyn to make good the bridge and foordes, till our whole horſe came thither: Theſe reaſons being ſo waighty, and proceeding from a Commander, of ſuch repute and long experience in war, and Lieu: Generall of that Army, were aſſented to by the Duke; ſo the foot paſſed the river, and for a good while after, Sir <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduke</hi> his ſouldiers aſsiſted with ſome of the Scottiſh horſe, ſeemed hard enough for the enemy, who ſeverall times were glad to retreat, but at laſt being over-powered by the enemies whole horſe, foot, and dragoons, both Sir <hi>Marmadukes</hi> and ours, were driven to quit the ground in diſorder. The Gen. ſeeing this (who was ſtill on the Moore expecting the reſidue of the horſe (which was on that ſide of the river) to come to us for their ſuccour, who were in fight: and finding that the enemy had there his whole Army, and ſtopped all the paſſages betwixt us and the bridge, on ſuch a ſuddain, that it was impoſsible for our Infantrie to come to us, or we to go to them by the bridge) gave order, that the few horſe which was on the Moore, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering they were able to execute nothing, nor yet recover the other ſide of the water) ſhould march to <hi>Monroe,</hi> which they did accordingly: To the Duke was then repreſented, an impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibillity of his getting to the foot, the enemy being ſo enterpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that it was ſafeſt for him to retreat alſo in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, towards the forces from <hi>Ireland;</hi> but he expreſsing more care of their preſervation, who were under his charge, then of his own, and therefore willing to incur any danger, rather then not be with his Army, rejects this counſell, and ſo through a narrow gap and over hedges, came into the town, from whence he thought to finde away unto the bridge; but inſtead thereof, found it full of the enemy, in purſuit of ſuch as were eſcaping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and divers ſhooting through the windows: yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the Duke made twice a ſtand in the town, and with few officers and gentlemen, beat back the enemy; where, I heard Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale</hi> tell him, that he was ſorry to ſee his Grace there, expoſing his own perſon to ſo great a hazzard, which he thought was very improper. The enemy coming on at laſt ſo thick, both with horſe and foot, there being not power to oppoſe them: The Duke although again he might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116914:5"/>
have gone to the horſe on the Moore, by another way, yet moſt unwilling ſtill to leave his Army, choſe rather to undergo any perill, and therefore found way to the river, which he intended to ſwim, not knowing of any paſſage; where being come, he accidentally came to a deep foord, through which he paſſed unto the Infantry.</p>
            <p>For defence of the bridge, ſeverall Brigades of our foot was drawn to it, which, for three hours time, was maintained with much reſolution and courage, but longer to keep it was impoſsible, conſidering the great advantages of the enemy, who on his ſide of the bridge had a high ground, with the ſhelter of hedges and houſes, on our ſide a diſcent (at the very end thereof) and then a plain, without ſo much as a buſh to favour us: ſo after hard diſputing, it was loſt.</p>
            <p>About a quarter of a mile from the bridge, on the top of a hill, we ſtaid with our foot, and about a hundred horſe: In the beginning of the night, by the advice of the Lieu. Generall <hi>Calander,</hi> and the major part of the officers that was there, it was reſolved to march towards Wiggin, which accordingly was done, the Cavalry being that way, from whom there was no return as yet, of any meſſenger that we had ſent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was uncertain to us, had we ſtaid never ſo long, we might have wanted their aſsiſtance: Here we loſt our Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and baggage, and in that nights march, many of our foot were loſt, the way being dark and exceeding dirty, and narrow.</p>
            <p>That night <hi>Middleton,</hi> by another way, marched with ſuch part of the Cavalry as he could get together in ſo ſhort a time, and the next morning came there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to Preſton bridge, where he found the enemy was, and that we were gone towards Wiggin; ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately he made after us, being very hotly purſued by the enemy, with whom he fought all the way till he came near us: in which action, our men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed ſo much gallantry, as that the enemies were forced again, though they had great bodies of horſe to make uſe of, their dragoons being within the hedges,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116914:5"/>
yet they loſt many men, namely Col. <hi>Thorney,</hi> whoſe death they much lamented: On our ſide was Collonel <hi>Hurrey</hi> ill (but not mortally) hurt, and divers troopers ſlain.</p>
            <p>About eight in the morning next day, being the eighteenth, we drew up in battalia, all our horſe and foot, on Standiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moore (two miles ſhort of Wiggin) expecting the enemy would give us battail: We ſtood in that poſture above four hours, till at laſt (there being no appearance that the enemy would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter) we marched towards Warrington; the rear to be brought up by <hi>Vandruſck</hi> which was performed with as much care and valour as was poſſible, <hi>(Middleton</hi> being with it alſo) Yet what with their dragoons, the deep ſtraight lanes, and the darkneſſe of the night, many of the foot (who had ſcarce ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten any thing for two dayes before) were loſt then, and next morning, before they came to Warrington.</p>
            <p>Being come to that town, Lieu. Gen. <hi>Baylie</hi> received order (by advice of the Officers that were there) to capitulate for the Infantry, no other way for their preſervation imaginable, being deſtitute of ammunition, a great part of their arms loſt, they wearied with the former marches, and divers wounded; ſo <hi>Baylie</hi> accepting of the beſt conditions he could procure from a victorious powerful enemy, parted with the foot at Warrington.</p>
            <p>From thence that morning, being the nineteenth, the Gen. and Lieu. Gen. marched with the horſe, and at night came to a place neer Malpas in Cheſhire, where <hi>Middleton</hi> was alſo, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brought up the rear of the Cavalrie, <hi>Vandruſck</hi> and divers other officers of horſe being hurt and taken priſoners; here it fell into conſideration, what courſe was beſt to ſteere for the ſafety of the Cavalrie; ſome adviſing for one place, and ſome for another; after much debate upon the whole, and all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences and diſcomodities fully pondred, it was the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the major part of the officers, that the beſt expedient in that condition was, to fetch a little compaſſe, endeavouring to get to Pomfret, and ſo more northward, as occaſion offerred, and this was reſolved upon. Here was the Duke himſelf ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded to leave the Cavalrie, and preſerve himſelf by withdrawing to Angleſey, or ſome other place of ſafety, which eaſily might have been effected, but he contemned it with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, as he did divers times ſithence, upon the like advice, he ſtill hoping to carry through the horſe, which doth evidence
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116914:6"/>
much worth, and the great care he had of thoſe that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his command. That night divers Collonels, and other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers privately forſook us, which was ſome diſheartning to the ſouldiers. In purſuite of the former reſolution, we mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched from thence betimes next morning, and quartered in the field at night, about a mile beyond Drayton in Shropſhire: From Drayton we removed before day next morning, being the 21. for Utoxater, where the laſt cataſtrophe was acted, but on our march that evening, <hi>Middleton</hi> who had the charge of the rear, more gallant, then like a wary commander, with a few men and himſelf, charged two troops of the Governour of Stafford his horſe, and ſo neer Stone was taken priſoner, which did too much contribute to our laſt misfortune, for this, and what formerly had hapned, took moſt of the ſouldiers with a panick fear, which by no art could be diſpoſſeſſed. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this news, and that the enemy was much ſtronger then thoſe of our rear, The Duke retires with the Army a good way, and upon a Moore draws it up, where we ſtaid about two hours till the rear came to us, and by that time it was night, and before we came to Utoxater, neer eleven of the clock, our horſe tired, and the ſouldiers exceedingly diſheartned. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of the ſouldiers diſmaiedneſſe, and averſeneſſe to march, moſt of them itching with a deſire of capitulation, The Duke with divers officers, perſiſt in the former reſolution of going Northward, therefore after that nights ſtay in Utoxater, which was ſpent with moſt of the horſe ſtanding in the ſtreets and about the town, by reaſon of the continuall alarums that were taken, by miſapprehenſion of the ſouldiers, we marched next morning towards Darbyſhire, and being a mile from the town, a ſtand was made on the top of a hill, and before the Duke was come thither, who was in the rear, the Earl of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander</hi> hapned on ſome occaſion to ſay (being ready to ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) thoſe who have good horſes, let them follow me, ſo went on, and many with him, the which left an impreſſion in the minds of moſt that his Lordſhip intended to be gone, not caring what became of them. Preſently after the Duke came to that hill, where he found all in a great diſcontent, and muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, not onely having deſire, but a poſitive reſolution, to march no further, and to return to Vtoxater, there to treat. The Duke exceedingly diſliking it, commanded them to march on,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116914:6"/>
and at Aſhburn in the Peak, upon further intelligence, what was fit to be done might be taken into conſideration, and that if neceſſity required a treaty, the field would procure bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conditions then ſuch a town: So the Duke did lead for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, thinking they would follow, but none did, unleſſe few, and ſome officers. The Duke ſeeing this diſobedience, and the moſt part ſtaying behinde in diſorder and confuſion, many of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers preſſing earneſtly that the Lieu. Gen. might be deſired to come back for further conſultation, the Gen. told them, that if they pleaſed they might recall him, which preſently they did. The Li. Gen. returning, he immediately paſled to his Nephew the Lord <hi>Levingſton,</hi> who was appointed to bring up the rear, and ſent him therewith to Vtoxater, ſtaying for the Duke on the former hill, to whom he ſaid, that he had ſent his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew back into the town, to prevent the enemy his coming thither: here, after ſome pauſe, it was found, that the pulſe of the ſouldiers did altogether beat back for the town, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declaring they would not march; and thereupon the Gen. Lieu. Gen. and the whole, went to Vtoxater, the Duke hoping that by refreſhment there of themſelves, and their horſes, that day, they might perhaps come to a better temper, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to advance in the evening; but inſtead thereof, they being generally poſſeſſed with an unalterable opinion of an impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billity to go through, in regard (as they ſaid) of ſuch multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of forces that was in the way, nothing could ſatisfie them but a capitulation. The Duke his determination of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing Northward, not at all abated, perceiving how they werebent, told them that he feared ere long they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent their obſtinacy and refuſall to march on, which in his judgement was feacible<hi>:</hi> and for a treaty, he knew not with whom they could conclude any, that might aſſure perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of conditions, there being none of the enemy neer, for ought he knew, that had ſufficient authority for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. There we ſtaid, and that night a great part of our ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers fearfully mutined, being ſo many as filled all the ſpatious Market place, and round about the Generals quarter, where every door was fain to be ſtrongly guarded, leſt they ſhould violently break in; in this unruly diſorder they continued moſt part of the night, having once taken away the Lieut. General his horſes, their pretence for the whole, being that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116914:7"/>
the officers intended to leave them, (as the Lord <hi>Kenmore</hi> had done that day, who was gone away with divers horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) whereas, (as they thought) good conditions might be obtained, if looked after<hi>:</hi> The Duke aſſured them for his part he would not leave them, nor be wanting in any thing that tended to their preſervation, which gave them ſatisfaction, yet were not fully appeaſed, till the next morning.</p>
            <p>This deteſtable mutiny, gave no ſmall advantage to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but proved the very bane and breakneck of our intentions, and as it was very diſobliging to the Duke, and full of diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſo muſt I needs praiſe his goodneſſe, in continuing his care of the ſouldiers; (though moſt of them very unworthy) whereas undoubtedly as yet, he might eaſily have compaſſed his own ſafety, and not become priſoner, could he have been willing to deſert them. Our going forward, being thereby rendred hopeleſſe, and ſome officers continuing their importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for a treaty, the Duke gave way (when no other remedy was left) that they ſhould treat with Col. <hi>Stone,</hi> Governour of Stafford, and ſome Committee men, who undertook to the Commiſſioners our officers had choſen for to treat, being three Collonels, <hi>Lockhart, Fowls,</hi> and <hi>Turner,</hi> that whatſoever they ſhould there agree to and promiſe, ſhould be ratified both by the Parliament and Army, and that no part of the conditions ſhould be unperformed. So the treaty began in the afternoon, on the 23. and the next day Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> being come neer with his forces, joyns in it.</p>
            <p>That day 23. the Earl of <hi>Calander</hi> with his Nephew, and divers other officers and ſouldiers, to the number of 200 or 300. went privately away (without aquainting the Duke) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt cauſed a falſe alarum to be made, the better (under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of going to repell the enemy) to get out of town unſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected.</p>
            <p>On the 24. about two in the afternoon in the time of the treaty, the Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> approaching neer with his forces, ſends a ſummons for all to yield to his mercie: The Duke acquaints him, that his officers had a treaty, and withall, ſent him to peruſe a letter from <hi>Lambert,</hi> approving of the ceſſation in order to the treaty, which was to continue till ſix in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, on the 25. and that aſſuredly our officers would be glad his Lordſhip would ſend ſome for his part likewiſe to treat;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116914:7"/>
to this there was no replie, but another ſummons ſent about midnight to the ſame effect as the former, requiring a ſpeedy reſolution: Whereupon the Duke ſent a Gentleman, by whom he expected the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> his conſent to the treaty, not doubting but his Lordſhip would have obſerved what ſhould be condiſcended to therein; The Gentleman returned not till about five in the morning, and with him came up to the Dukes chamber, Collonel <hi>Wayte,</hi> Maſter <hi>Peters,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> his Secretary, who (as they alleadged) were by the Lord <hi>Grays</hi> direction going to the treaty<hi>:</hi> The Duke was ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the bed by reaſon of an exceſſive pain in his legs (which divers other officers were ill troubled with) by the wearing of hard boots, unput off, for divers dayes and nights to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; after ſome expreſſion of civility had mutually paſt, M. <hi>Peters</hi> asked the Generall, if he would be my Lord <hi>Gray</hi> his priſoner, he anſwered; (without any the leaſt trouble, diſmay, or appearance of care of himſelf, though queſtionleſſe much grieved at the condition his Army was reduced unto) that in regard of the treaty, he knew nor whether he was to be a priſoner or no; but if ſo neceſſitated, he had rather become my Lord <hi>Grays</hi> priſoner, with whom he was well acquainted, then another? Then Maſter <hi>Peters</hi> offered the Duke to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what things he had of value, if they were delivered to him<hi>:</hi> The Duke thankfully anſwered, that he had loſt all at Preſton, and therefore had nothing he would trouble him with; and ſo for that time they parted.</p>
            <p>Much about this time the treaty was concluded, which was no otherwiſe performed then as if never any ſuch thing had been in agitation.</p>
            <p>Whereof one Article was, that neither officer nor ſouldier ſhould be plundred, or have ought taken from him, except arms; Yet before nine a clock that morning, the Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> with their forces, and the Countrey Moorelanders, came thick upon us: <hi>Lambert</hi> taking ſome pains, by beating off his ſouldiers, to reſtrain their violence; nevertheleſſe, he, with the Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> were imediately plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, notwithſtanding the agreement, to ſhare betwixt them the horſes of the Duke and his ſeruants; not leaving one for the Duke himſelf to ride upon. I will ſpare to tell (after the Duke was gone away with the Lord <hi>Gray,)</hi> what cunning was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116914:8"/>
uſed, Firſt, with fair promiſes, to procure confeſſion what money we had hid, or given others to keep, and how after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they diſpoiled us: and thus was our meaſure of unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, in what was wanting by the diſobedience, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny of our own ſouldiers, made full, with the nonperformance and too hard uſage of our adverſaries.</p>
            <p>I conclude, as the prologue to our miſery, was the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and unavoidable length of time protracted, before the Army could be prepared in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by means of the great obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the adverſe party and the Miniſters, which thereby gave way to the overthrow and utter diſenabling of our friends in <hi>England,</hi> and to the ſtrength and uniting of our enemies to make head againſt us: So at Vtoxater, the mutiny of our ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, with their and ſome officers refuſall to march, or obey any order, was the cauſe of this unfortunate Epilogue, in the delivery of our Cavalrie.</p>
            <p>And for our march to Lancaſhire, and there dividing our forces, ſome out of prejudice, malice, or partiality, will perhaps deſcant upon it, although it was done upon ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation, and reaſons, as would then have ſufficiently ſatisfied their judgements who now do cenſure it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the event, without conſidering, that the wiſeſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and decrees of men, are not infallible, but ſubject to errours<hi>:</hi> Nor could any aſcertain us of better ſucceſſe, had we gone to Yorkſhire, or framed our proceedings after all the wayes that mans wit can now fancy had been to our advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and declined theſe we followed.</p>
            <p>This Army, I confeſſe, was conſiderable, but not ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as I underſtand report makes it, by the enemies deviſe (a cuſtomary trick) to acquire the more honour in van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing, by how much the greater we were in number: For it, and Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdales,</hi> had they all been together, (as there was of both a great part from us) would have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to no more then five thouſand horſe, and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand foot, beſides baggage men, and pedees, of which there was too too many, and whereof we have certain cauſe to repent.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs ſay, that too much liberty of plundering was permitted in the Scottiſh Army, (though not the third part of what hath been rumor'd) and I cannot but blame the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116914:8"/>
for impunity<hi>:</hi> Yet I am confident the Generall him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf knew little of it, for I am ſure he exceedingly abhord it; And at <hi>Kirby Thure</hi> did cauſe proclamation to be made (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt plundering) through the whole army, thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing death, for the ſmalleſt offence in that nature, and ſhortly after ſome were hanged accordingly; ſo far was he from deſiring grievance, or burthen to the Countrey, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in proviſion, or otherwiſe, was taken for him and his ſervants, but was paid for to the full value; and when a compoſition of a ſumme conſiderable was offered unto him, he ſaid he would have nothing to do with it; Vpon which, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing, I heard an officer of quality much diſcommend the Duke for refuſing, in regard of the vaſt expence he had been at. I wiſh others had been ſo free from avarice, ſurely it had been happy.</p>
            <p>Yours of the which I received juſt now, gives me notice a relation made at <hi>London,</hi> few dayes after our disbanding, ſo falſe, as that I wonder how malice it ſelf could invent it: both times when Collonel <hi>Wayte</hi> came to the Dukes Chamber, at Vtoxater, I with divers officers were preſent, and till his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture there continued, uſing that as our ſanctuary from the ſouldiers violence, ſo long as the Duke remained in it, though afterwards it was the place of my plundering. It is true the Duke was upon his bed till neer the time of his going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, for the cauſe before mentioned, and a little while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he went out, one of the enemy took his ſword, which was over the beds head, which the Duke ſeeing, did deſire him to give it to the Lord <hi>Gray;</hi> whereupon (his Lordſhip not being preſent) that party delivered it to Collonel <hi>Wayte,</hi> for that purpoſe; it hung in a torn black ſtitched belt, not worth five ſhillings. At the ſame inſtant, I ſaw Lieu. Collonel <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> give him the blue rich embroidered Scarf, (which divers times the Lieu. Collonel had worn, for ſix years before) in hopes to obtain Collonel <hi>Wayte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> his protection from further pillage, which was promiſed, but I fear neglected; for I ſaw the Gentleman, within an hour after, with ſcarce clothes to cover him: But nothing more untrue then that the Duke deſired Collonel <hi>Wayte,</hi> or any other perſon, to reſcue him from the ſouldiers, or that he diſcovered any fear, by words, looks, or actions, and probably he was free from any; for I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116914:9"/>
heard him wiſh moſt earneſtly, both there, and ſince our coming from Preſton, that his life were loſt, before he ſaw his Army come to ruine, which abundance of officers are able to juſtifie. Neither had Collonel <hi>Wayte</hi> from the Duke any Scarf or Georg, at that time, for the George he wore it when I laſt ſaw him at his going on horſeback, and I am credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, by a Gentleman from Leiceſterſhire lately come hither, that he ſaw him wear it above a week after, in Leiceſter, when <hi>Wayte</hi> was returned from <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I underſtand, that many falſe and unworthy aſperſions have been caſt upon this Army; as that divers members thereof had brought in their Wives and Families, purpoſely, to plant and inhabit in <hi>England,</hi> and that it was uſuall amongſt the ſouldiers, to carry away little children, which the parents were conſtrained to redeem for money, then which (as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things elſe reported of this Army) nothing more untrue, and were meerly invented to incenſe <hi>England,</hi> and bring the greater odium upon us.</p>
            <p>Thus have I laid down the truth, without any dreſſe, var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, or partiallity, which you or any other upon doubt, may have juſtified by many hundreds, if you pleaſe to make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inquiry.</p>
            <p>In regard I have been ſo tedious (till the next occaſion) I ſhall ſay nothing of my own particular, and the poſt is ready to depart, my ſelf going to Gorcum; when I am returned from thence expect again to hear from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your, &amp;c.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Roterdam,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
